Geneviève Saint-Pierre Papers, 1904-1962
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Geneviève Saint-Pierre Papers
1904-1962
Saint-Pierre, Geneviève
MS 137
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
French travel writer and hunter. Papers include travel notes and photographs from Equador, Mexico, Western U.S., and Australia. Also correspondence, autobiographical note, and published writings. Most material is in French and Breton languages.
Biographical Note
Geneviève Saint-Pierre, a notable traveler and hunter, was born in Breton, France in 1872. She traveled to Quito, Ecuador on horseback in 1899, hunted moose in "the wilds of Canada" and wild boar in the Yuma territory of Arizona, California, and Mexico; went up the Peace River in Alberta, Canada, in 1908, and journeyed to Sydney, Australia in 1928. Saint-Pierre also wrote articles and a book, and published excerpts from her journals. She also translated works from the Breton language to French in order to promote her native language and culture of Brittany.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Geneviève Saint-Pierre Papers include writings, clippings, publications, and photographs. The writings include travel journals (in French) and notes from a hunting expedition in the Western U.S. in 1907, her travels in Canada, and a trip to Sydney, Australia in 1928. Photographic images include scenes of Ecuador (1899), the Grand Canyon and the American west, and Mexico. Letters from Saint-Pierre to Sophia Smith Collection Director Margaret Storrs Grierson (1947-62) include some biographical information. Published writings include articles by Breton author René Leroux (pseud. Meven Mordiern); Breton publications: Almanak ar Breizad (1943) and Iverzon gwelet gant Eur Vretonez (1933), with a French translation by Saint-Pierre; and a French novel about the Incas entitled Les Emerudes de L'Inca (1923) by Vefa (Geneviève) de Saint-Pierre and F. De Saint-Pierre. The writings are primarily in French and Breton languages. There is also a typescript of translations into French by Saint-Pierre of Breton texts by Maodez Glanndour, including his poems "Imram," "Milc hwid rear Serrnoz," Sonennou berr," and "Feuilles défachées."
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Geneviève Saint-Pierre donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection circa 1948. Breton texts by Maodez Glanndour, with typescript translations by Saint-Pierre, were donated to Neilson Library in 1947 and transferred to the SSC in 2007.
Search Terms
Australia--Description and travel--Sources; Breton literature; Canada--Description and travel--Sources; Central America--Description and travel--Sources; West (U.S.)--Description and travel--Sources; Women adventurers--Biography--Sources; Women hunters--Biography--Sources; Glanndour, Maodez; Leroux, René, 1878-; Mordiern, Meven (pseud.); Saint-Pierre, Geneviève
- Biographical note (in French), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Almanak ar Breizad (contains article on Saint-Pierre's great uncle), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Clippings by René Leroux (1948) and correspondence from Geneviève Saint-Pierre to Margaret Storrs Grierson, 1947-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Notes du Voyage": journal (in French), 12 March 1907- (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Newspaper articles and clippings, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Articles by Saint-Pierre (in French), 1904-10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous pictures, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Scrapbook of Canada trip, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Les Emeraudes de L'Inca, by Geneviève Saint-Pierre, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Journal du Voyage á Sydney, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Yverzon gwelet gant Eur Vretonez, a book on Ireland in the Breton language and translation into French by Saint-Pierre, 1933, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Translations into French by Saint-Pierre of Breton texts by Maodez Glanndour, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "L'Iriande Telle que Je l'ai Vue": typescript (by Saint-Pierre ?), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)